Guide to the Ruth Barcan Marcus Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Departmental files, 1973-2008; Series III
  - Hartigan, John, 1991 (Box 37, Folder 14)
  - Job search
    - Candidate evaluations, 1983-1984 (Box 37, Folder 15)
    - Philosophy of Mind candidate evaluations, 1995-1996 (Box 37, Folder 16)
  - Letter to faculty concerning "candy file" incident, 1985 (Box 37, Folder 17)
  - Personnel, 1980 (Box 37, Folder 18)
  - Procedures - appointments, 1982 (Box 37, Folder 19)
  - Recruitment, 1991-1996 (Box 37, Folder 20)
- Notebooks, 1947-1978; Series IV (Box 38, Folder 1-8)
  This series consists of notebooks kept by Ruth Barcan Marcus over a 30-year span from the late 1940s through the late 1970s. The content of the notebooks is a curious mix of notes on Marcus' research, writings, and classroom instruction, as well as drafts of correspondence, schedules and to-do lists, and personal notes. Many of the notebooks contain extensive mathematical formulas and problems, most likely related to her work in the field of modal logic.
- Teaching and course files, 1959-1995; Series V
  This series consists of notes, outlines, syllabi, schedules, and other materials related to Ruth Barcan Marcus' teaching career. The bulk of these materials were produced during Marcus' tenure as a professor at Yale, though the dates of some files correspond to her academic appointments at the University of Illinois at Chicago and Northwestern University, respectively. Many of the materials are identified by the specific course taught, while others are identified by topic with no indication of the course for which documents were used.
  - General
    - Courses
      - General, 1974 (Box 39, Folder 1)
      - Outlines, 1982-1983 (Box 39, Folder 2)
      - Schedules, 1974 (Box 39, Folder 3)
      - Syllabi, 1972-1974 (Box 39, Folder 4)
    - Notes, Undated (Box 39, Folder 5-8)
    - Philosophy reading lists, 1976-1979 (Box 39, Folder 9)
  - Courses, individual
    - Philosophy 97-6, draft quiz, Undated (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - Philosophy 101, 1965, undated (Box 40, Folder 2)
    - Philosophy 204/504
      - General, 1980-1982, undated (Box 40, Folder 3)
      - Examination, 1980 (Box 40, Folder 4-5)
      - Example VII, chapter 6, Undated (Box 40, Folder 6)
      - Exercises, 1982, undated (Box 40, Folder 7-8)
      - Handouts, Undated (Box 40, Folder 9-19)
      - Mates, Elementary Logic, chapters 1-6, exercises and answers, 1979-1981, undated (Box 40, Folder 20-22)
      - Notes, Undated (Box 40, Folder 23)
      - Paper topics, 1982 (Box 40, Folder 24)
      - Quizzes, 1978-1982 (Box 40, Folder 25-31)
      - Reading lists, Cross Campus Library, 1979-1982 (Box 40, Folder 32-33)
      - Readings, week one, Undated (Box 40, Folder 34)
      - Reminders, 1982 (Box 40, Folder 35)
      - Replacement theorem, Undated (Box 40, Folder 36)
      - Sign-up sheets, discussion sections, graduate topics, 1981 (Box 40, Folder 37)
      - Syllabus, 1980-1982 (Box 40, Folder 38-40)
    - Philosophy 440A, Belief, 1995, undated (Box 40, Folder 41)
    - Philosophy 451/651
      - Reserve book lists, Undated (Box 40, Folder 42-43)
      - Syllabus, Circa 1980, undated (Box 40, Folder 44-45)
  - Directed Studies, 1980-1991 (Box 41, Folder 1-7)
  - Philosophers, individual
    - Aristotle, 1971, undated (Box 41, Folder 8)
    - Austin, Undated (Box 41, Folder 9)
    - Austin, Frege, Tarski, Undated (Box 41, Folder 10)
    - Austin, Wittgenstein, Descartes, Wisdom, Undated (Box 41, Folder 11)
    - Ayer, Undated (Box 41, Folder 12)
    - Baier, Undated (Box 41, Folder 13)
    - Bentham, Undated (Box 41, Folder 14)
    - Berkeley, Undated (Box 41, Folder 15)
    - Carnap, Undated (Box 41, Folder 16)
    - Descartes, Undated (Box 41, Folder 17)
    - Dewey, Undated (Box 41, Folder 18)
    - Hare, Undated (Box 41, Folder 19)
    - Hart, Undated (Box 41, Folder 20)
    - Hobbes, Undated (Box 41, Folder 21-22)
    - Hume, Undated (Box 41, Folder 23)
    - James, Undated (Box 41, Folder 24)
    - Kant, Undated (Box 41, Folder 25)
    - Locke, Undated (Box 41, Folder 26)
    - Mates, 1987, undated (Box 41, Folder 27-31)
    - Meinong, Undated (Box 41, Folder 32)
    - Mill, John Stuart, 1973 (Box 41, Folder 33)
    - Moore, Undated (Box 42, Folder 1-6)
    - Pierce, Undated (Box 42, Folder 7)
    - Plato, Undated (Box 42, Folder 8-11)
    - Russell, Undated (Box 42, Folder 12-13)
    - Ryle, Undated (Box 42, Folder 14-15)
    - Santayana, Undated (Box 42, Folder 16)
    - Stevenson, Undated (Box 42, Folder 17)
    - Stevenson and Rawls, Undated (Box 42, Folder 18)
    - Urmson, Undated (Box 42, Folder 19)
    - Wisdom, Undated (Box 42, Folder 20)
    - Wittgenstein, Undated (Box 42, Folder 21)
  - Subjects
    - Alternative logic, Undated (Box 42, Folder 22-23)
    - Analytical philosophy, 1974, undated (Box 42, Folder 24-25)
    - Diagonal argument, Undated (Box 42, Folder 26)
    - Ethics, 1972-1974, 1994, undated (Box 42, Folder 27-31)
    - Logic, 1959, 1971-1983, undated (Box 42, Folder 32-37)
    - Modal logic
      - General, 1974-1984, undated (Box 42, Folder 38-44)
      - Chellas, 1970 (Box 42, Folder 45)
      - Completeness, Undated (Box 42, Folder 46)
      - Extra theorems lists, Undated (Box 42, Folder 47)
      - Lecture notes, 1977 (Box 42, Folder 48-49)
      - Notations, Undated (Box 42, Folder 50)
      - Required reading list, 1980 January (Box 42, Folder 51)
      - Take home examination, 1980 March (Box 42, Folder 52)
    - Philosophical logic
      - Completeness of SC, Undated (Box 42, Folder 53)
      - Exercises, chapter 7, 1976, undated (Box 42, Folder 54)
      - Final examination, 1973 (Box 42, Folder 55)
      - Final examination make-up, 1976 (Box 42, Folder 56)
      - Quizzes, Undated (Box 42, Folder 57-58)
      - Readings, 1979 (Box 42, Folder 59)
      - Syllabus, 1976, 1987 (Box 42, Folder 60-61)
    - Systematic logic, 1968, undated (Box 42, Folder 62)
- Writings, speeches, and lectures, 1942-2010; Series VI
  This series comprises scholarly papers, articles, and audtio recordings of speeches and lectures by Ruth Barcan Marcus, as well as notes, outlines, and correspondence related to her writings. The bulk of materials concerns the topics of modal logic and belief, two of Marcus' foremost research interests. The paper, "Women in Philosophy," delivered at an unspecified conference or event, details both Marcus' own experience as a woman in the field of philosophy, as well as her perspective on the status and role of women in philosophy throughout her life and career.
  - "Are Possible, Non-Actual Objects Real?", 1997 (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - "Bar-On on Spinoza's Ontological Proof", 1983 (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - Belief
    - Animal, 1988 (Box 43, Folder 3)
    - Animal and infant thought, 1996-1999, undated (Box 43, Folder 4)
    - Appiah, Anthony and Curtis Brown, 1988-1993 (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - Bern University and Henry Lauener, 1993-1998 (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - Brown, Curtis, 1989 (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - Journal of Philosophy proof, 1982 (Box 43, Folder 8)
    - Notes, 1981-1986, undated (Box 43, Folder 9-12)
    - Papers, 1989-1991, undated (Box 43, Folder 13-14)
    - Ravizza, Mark, 1989 (Box 43, Folder 15)
    - Soames, Scott, comments, 1980 (Box 43, Folder 16)
  - Boston Colloquium for the Philosophy of Science, Ruth Barcan Marcus paper, 1962 February 8; 2 (Box 45–46)
    Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  - Brown convocation address, 1979 (Box 43, Folder 17-18)
  - "Classes and Attributes in Extended Modal Systems", 1963 (Box 43, Folder 19)
  - "Classes, Collections, and Individuals", 1974 (Box 43, Folder 20-21)
  - Comments on paper of David Wiggins, 1974 (Box 43, Folder 22)
  - Comments on Stocker, Undated (Box 43, Folder 23)
  - "The Deduction Theorem in a Functional Calculus of First Order Based on Strict Implication" in Journal of Symbolic Logic, 1946 December (Box 43, Folder 24)
  - Descartes, Spinoza, and Liebniz, handwritten drafts of papers, Circa 1942 (Box 43, Folder 25)
  - "Dispensing with Possibilia", 1976 (Box 43, Folder 26-27)
  - "Essential Attribution", Undated (Box 43, Folder 28)
  - "Extensionality", Circa 1990s (Box 43, Folder 29)
  - "Flowers and Famines", 1992; 1 (Box 47)
  - "How to Russell-Kaplan a Kripke", 1982 November (Box 43, Folder 30)
  - Kripke, Saul, "Truth" lectures at Princeton, 1975 June 4-7; 6 (Box 48–53)
    Lecture two, box 52, includes questions from A. Morton, C. Parsons, D. Levin, P. Benacerraf, and G. Harman.
  - "The Identity of Individuals in a Strict Functional Calculus of Second Order" in Journal of Symbolic Logic, 1947 March (Box 43, Folder 31)
  - "Intellectual Trajectories", 2006 (Box 43, Folder 32)
  - Introduction to Themes from Kaplan, 1987 (Box 43, Folder 33)
  - "Liberty" and "Personal Identity", Undated; 1 (Box 54)
  - Modalities, 1993-2009 (Box 44, Folder 1-2)
  - "Morals and Motives", 1991; 1 (Box 55)
  - "Moral Dilemmas and Consistency", 1980, undated (Box 44, Folder 3-4)
  - "Note on Identity and Substitutivity in a Modal System", Undated (Box 44, Folder 5)
  - "On Some Post-1920s Views of Russell on Particularity, Identity, and Individuation," Mérites et Limities du Méthodes Logiques en Philosophie, colloquium, 1984 June (Box 44, Folder 6)
  - Physicalia, Undated (Box 44, Folder 7)
  - "Possibles That Are Almost Actual," Ruth Marcus and Storrs McCall, Undated (Box 44, Folder 8)
  - "A Proposed Solution to a Puzzle about Belief", Undated (Box 44, Folder 9)
  - "Quantification and Ontology", 1972 (Box 44, Folder 10)
  - Smith and Soames, American Philosophical Association (APA), Boston meeting, 1994 December 28; 3 (Box 56–58)
  - "Some Revisionary Proposals about Belief and Believing", Circa 1990s (Box 44, Folder 11)
  - Speech to Phi Kappa Phi, 1975 (Box 44, Folder 12)
  - Spinoza, Undated (Box 44, Folder 13-14)
  - "Women in Philosophy", 2010 (Box 44, Folder 15)
- Electronic files, Circa 1980-2011; Series VII (Box 59)
  This series consists of one 8" floppy disk, one 3.5" floppy disk, one DVD-R, and two flash drives.
  Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.